Guide to the Bern Boyle Papers MSS.341
Fales Library and Special Collections
Bern Boyle Papers
1976 - 2000
1979-1989
Fales Library and Special Collections
Boyle, Bern
MSS.341
10 Linear Feet
Bern Boyle was a photographer, curator, actor, filmmaker, and LGBT activist. The Bern Boyle Photography Collection comprises his work in the form of contact sheets, negatives, photographs, and slides. In addition, this collection includes correspondence, postcards, press clippings, promotional material, and Boyle's 8mm and 16mm films.
Scope and Content
The Bern Boyle Papers comprises Boyle's work in the form of contact sheets, negatives, photographs, and slides. Subjects include architecture, city streetscapes, street art, and gay pride parades; locations are primarily New York City and San Francisco, but also include Mexico, other Latin American locations, Miami, and Paris. This collection also includes Boyle's photobooth pictures of both himself and his friends. Although there is some staged portraiture (eg. "Tattoo Mike"), more casual street shots and special events photography dominate the collection. In addition, this collection includes coursework, a small selection of press clippings and promotional material, personal correspondence, and printed ephemera.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into the following series:
Series I: Photographic Materials
Subseries A: Locations Photography includes contact sheets, negatives, photographs, and slides organized alphabetically by location.
Subseries B: Portraiture preserves contact sheets, negatives, photographs, and slides. Subjects include Boyle' s "Photobooth" and "Tattoo Mike" series, as well as snapshots of bodybuilders, drag queens, friends, LGBT activists, and unique hair styles. All records are arranged alphabetically by original title or subject category.
Subseries C: Coursework holds photographic materials not directly associated with the previous subseries in addition to lesson packets associated with the photo-retouching course that Boyle took in 1983. All contents are arranged alphabetically by original title or subject category.
Subseries D: Photobooth Pictures comprises primarily of self-portraits. These materials are retained in Boyle's original arrangement scheme: "Friends"; "Bern with Friends"; "Bern Solo"; "Years 1981, 1982, 1984, 1985, 1986 (by month), 1991, 1992"; "Parents"; and "Miscellaneous Photos."
Series II: Exhibitions Press includes press clippings, "Photobooth" promotional material, and a small selection of Boyle's "Roadkill" series. All contents are arranged alphabetically by subject category.
Series III: Postcards and Correspondence
Subseries A: Personal Correspondence is arranged chronologically.
Subseries B: Postcards and Printed Ephemera includes announcements from galleries and performance venues, in addition to commercially printed postcards of Boyle's work. This arrangement reflects the categories of the archive's original arrangement scheme. Gracie Mansion postcards are grouped separately while postcards from other galleries and performance spaces are arranged alphabetically by venue.
Series IV: Film preseves Boyle's 8mm and 16mm film reels. All elements are arranged alphabetically by original title or subject category.
Biographical Note
Born in 1951, Bern Boyle received his B.A. from Villanova University and an M.A. in Teaching English from Hunter College. In 1988, he received an M.A. in Museum Studies from The City College of New York. He lived in Philadelphia, San Francisco, and New York City.
In 1973, Boyle helped to found Giovanni's Room in Philadelphia, the nation's oldest and largest LGBT bookstore and cultural center, and is also credited with founding the San Francisco International LGBT Film Festival in 1976, (today it is known as the Frameline Film Festival). In New York City he lived in the East Village and was known for his participation in the mail art scene. An active member of the New York City film community, Boyle acted in the 1975 horror parody film "Thundercrack," and appeared as himself in the 1990 film "Silence = Death" alongside Keith Haring, David Wojnarowicz, and other downtown artists and writers struggling with AIDS. He also directed a small number of short films and documentaries.
Boyle is most well known for his curatorial and photographic work. Among the many art shows he curated are "The North American Coastal New Wave" at the Foro de Arte Contemporaneo, Mexico City; "Mexican Illustrators: 1920-1950" at the Anglo-Mexican Institute of Culture, Mexico City; "The History of Books for the Blind" at The Catholic Center, New York City; and "Booth: Photo Booth Work by Herman Costa" at St. Mark's Graphics, New York City.
As a photographer, Boyle documented a wide range of subjects, from street art in Alphabet City and Loisaida, to portraits of Coney Island sideshow performer Michael Wilson (aka "The Illustrated Man" or "Tattoo Mike"). In 1986, amidst the panic of the AIDS epidemic and dismay at learning of many of his friends' diagnoses (and perhaps his own), he photographed himself once a day using a photobooth, which ultimately led him to curate the "Photomaton" exhibition in 1987, which was the first exhibition to showcase the work of artists working with photobooth technology.
Bern Boyle died of AIDS-related complications on June 17, 1992 in New York City.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open to researchers. Series III: Film components are not available for consultation. Please contact the Fales Library and Special Collections, fales.library@nyu.edu, 212-998-2596.
Provenance
The collection was donated to NYU's Fales Library & Special Collections by Sur Rodney (Sur) in 2012 and 2013.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Access to audiovisual materials in this collection is available through digitized access copies. Researchers may view an item's original container, but the media themselves are not available for playback because of preservation concerns. Materials that have already been digitized are noted in the collection's finding aid and can be requested in our reading room. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact nyuspecialcollections@nyu.edu with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Negatives (photographic); Contact sheets.; Color photographs.; Black-and-white photographs.; Photographs.; Portrait photography.; LGBTQ+ activism; Manuals.; Film (material by form); Amateur films |x Production and direction.; Printed ephemera.; Photography -- Exhibitions -- New York (State) -- New York.; Promotional materials; Fliers (printed matter); Clippings (information artifacts); 8mm (photographic film size); 16mm; Pamphlets.; Posters.; Announcements.; Postcards.; Limelight (Gallery: New York, N.Y.); Booklets.; Self-portraits; Female impersonators.; Photography of bodybuilders; photobooth pictures; Gay film festivals.; Landscape photography.; Slides (photographs); AIDS (Disease); Mexico City (Mexico); Miami Beach (Fla.); Paris (France); San Francisco (Calif.); AIDS activists -- New York (State) -- New York; Gays -- Political activity -- New York (State) -- New York.; Gay activists -- New York (State) -- New York.; Film.; Gracie Mansion Gallery; Wilson, Michael; Boyle, Bern
- Series I: Photographic Materials
  Scope and Contents
  Series I: Photographic Materials is arranged into four subseries: Locations Photography, Portraiture, Coursework, and Photobooth Pictures. Formats include contact sheets, negatives, photographs, slides, and booklets. The first three subseries' materials are arranged alphabetically by location or subject category while Subseries D: Photobooth Pictures are retained in Boyle's original arrangement scheme.
  - Subseries A: Locations Photography
    - California Slides: Sculptures, Signs, Storefronts, 1989 (Binder 1)
    - Latin America Negatives: Streetscapes, Portraits, Art, undated (Binder 2)
    - Latin America Negatives, Contact Sheet; Streetscapes, Portraits, Art, undated (Binder 3)
    - Mexico Slides: Art, Architecture, People, 1979 - 1981 (Binder 4)
    - Mexico Slides: Modern Mexican Art, 1980 - 1990 (Binder 5)
    - Miami Slides: Neon Signs, Marquees, Storefronts, 1976 - 1989 (Binder 6)
    - New York City Slides: Streetscapes, 1979 - 1987 (Binder 7)
    - New York City Slides: Graffiti, Storefronts, 1979 - 1989 (Binder 8)
    - New York City Slides: Portraits, Street Art, Newspapers, 1980 - 1990 (Binder 9)
    - New York City Slides: People, 1987 - 1989 (Binder 10)
    - New York City Slides: Murals, Graffiti, 1979 - 1988 (Binder 11)
    - New York City Contact Sheets, Negatives: Assorted Subjects, 1988 (Binder 12)
    - New York City Negatives: Portraits, Streetscapes, undated (Binder 13)
    - New York/East Coast Negatives: "People and Places, 1 of 2", undated (Binder 14)
    - New York/East Coast Negatives: "People and Places, 2 of 2", undated (Binder 15)
    - New York/East Coast 4" x 5" Negatives, undated (Box 36, Folder 1)
    - New York/East Coast Contact Sheets, Negatives, undated (Box 36, Folder 2)
    - New York/Latin America Contact Sheets: Graffiti, Signs, Portraits, Nudes, undated (Binder 16)
    - New York/Mexico Contact Sheets, Negatives: Portraits, Tattoos, Streetscapes, 1986 - 1987 (Binder 17)
    - Paris Assorted Media: Assorted Subjects, 1986 (Binder 18)
    - Paris Negatives; Streetscapes, Graffiti, undated (Binder 19)
    - San Francisco Slides: People, Gay Pride, 1976 - 1979 (Binder 20)
    - San Francisco Slides: People, Gay Pride, Streetscapes, 1977 - 1989 (Binder 21)
    - San Francisco Contact Sheets: People, Gay Pride [1 of 2], undated (Binder 22)
    - San Francisco Contact Sheets: People, Gay Pride [2 of 2], undated (Binder 23)
    - San Francisco Negatives: Gay Pride, Photos of Event Flyers, Portraits, People, undated (Binder 24)
    - Travels: Florida, Latin America, Paris, Philadelphia; Texas Slides: People, Parades, Streetscapes, 1976 - 1988 (Binder 25)
  - Subseries B: Portraiture
    - Miscellaneous Photographs of People and Places, 1990s (Binder 40)
    - People Pre-1990 Slides: Part 1 of 2, circa 1990 (Binder 26)
    - People Pre-1990 Slides: Part 2 of 2, circa 1990 (Binder 27)
    - Photobooth Slides, 1986 (Binder 28)
    - Portraits and Headshots Slides, 1986 (Binder 29)
    - Portraits and Headshots Negatives, undated (Binder 30)
    - Potraits and Self-Potraits Slides, 1978 - 1983 (Binder 31)
    - Tattoo Contact Sheets, Postcard, Slides: Staged and Casual Portraiture, 1979 - 1988 (Binder 32)
    - Tattoo Mike: Photograph, Exhibition Postcards, 1988, 2000 (Box 36, Folder 3)
  - Subseries C: Coursework
    - 3" x 3" Art Gallery with Neon "Expose" Sign Photograph, undated (Box 36, Folder 6)
    - "35mm of Sculpture Guru Dan H" Photographs, Negatives, undated (Box 36, Folder 10)
    - Assorted 3" x 5" Photographs, Negatives, undated (Box 36, Folder 5)
    - Assorted Contact Sheets, undated (Binder 35)
    - Loose Negatives, undated (Box 36, Folder 7)
    - New Stone Age Slides, 1981 (Box 36, Folder 8)
    - Photo-Retouching Lesson Booklets 1-3, 1981 (Box 36, Folder 11)
    - Photo-Retouching Lesson Booklets 4-6, 1983 (Box 36, Folder 12)
    - Photo-Retouching Lesson Booklets 7-9, 1983 (Box 36, Folder 13)
    - Photo-Retouching Lesson Booklets 10-12, 1983 (Box 36, Folder 14)
    - Photo-Retouching Lesson Booklets 13-15, 1983 (Box 36, Folder 15)
    - Photo-Retouching Lesson Materials, Work Samples, 1983 (Box 36, Folder 16)
    - Sylvester Negatives, undated (Box 36, Folder 9)
  - Subseries D: Photobooth Pictures
    Arrangement
    These photographs are retained in Boyle's original categories:
    [1] "Friends"
    [2] "Bern with Friends"
    [3] "Bern Solo"
    [4] "Years 1981, 1982, 1984, 1985, 1986 (by month), 1991, 1992"
    [5] "Parents"
    [6] "Miscellaneous Photos"
    - Photobooth Pictures: Categories 1 - 6, 1980-1992 (Binder 38)
    - Photobooth Pictures: Category 6, 1980-1992 (Binder 39)
- Series II: Exhibitions Press
  Series II: Exhibitions Press includes promotional material and are arranged alphabetically.
  - Exhibition Information, Press Clippings, 1979 - 1987 (Binder 33)
  - "Photobooth" Press Clippings, "Bar Time" Flyer, 1979 - 1987 (Box 36, Folder 4)
  - Press Clippings, Roadkill Slides, 1981 - 1989 (Binder 34)
- Series III: Postcards and Correspondence
  Series III: Postcards and Correspondence is separated into two subseries: Personal Correspondence and Postcards and Printed Ephemera. Boyle's Personal Correspondence is arranged chronologically while the groupings of Postcards and Printed Ephemera reflect the categories of the archive's original arrangement scheme. Gracie Mansion postcards are grouped separately while postcards from other galleries and performance spaces are arranged alphabetically by venue.
  - Subseries A: Personal Correspondence
    - Personal Correspondence, 1977-1984 (Box 41, Folder 1)
    - Personal Correspondence, 1985-1987 (Box 41, Folder 2)
    - Personal Correspondence, 1988 (Box 41, Folder 3)
    - Personal Correspondence, undated (Box 41, Folder 4)
    - Unidentified Artwork, undated (Box 41, Folder 5)
  - Subseries B: Postcards and Printed Ephemera
    - Postcards by Bern Boyle, 1977 - 1983; undated (Binder 40)
    - Gracie Mansion Gallery Postcards, circa 1980s (Box 41, Folder 6)
    - Gracie Mansion Gallery Postcards, circa 1980s (Box 41, Folder 7)
    - Venues A - D, circa 1980s (Box 41, Folder 8)
    - Venues E - J, circa 1980s (Box 41, Folder 9)
    - Venues L - O, circa 1980s (Box 41, Folder 10)
    - Venues P, circa 1980s (Box 41, Folder 11)
    - Venues R - S, circa 1980s (Box 41, Folder 12)
    - Venues T - W, circa 1980s (Box 41, Folder 13)
- Series IV: Film
  Series III: Film includes Boyle's 8mm and 16mm reels. These objects are arranged alphabetically by original title or subject category.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Films are not available for researcher use.
  - Around the House, undated; ID: 341.0019 (Box 42, Media ID: 341.0019)
    Currently unavailable until duplication occurs.
    Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements Note
    Original format: 8mm, 50 ft
  - Around the House 2, undated; ID: 341.0020 (Box 42, Media ID: 341.0020)
  - Around the House 3, undated; ID: 341.0024 (Box 42, Media ID: 341.0024)
  - "Bern's Haircut", undated; ID: 341.0001 (Box 42, Media ID: 341.0001)
    Original format: 8mm, 400 ft
    Original Container Annotation: [1] "Bern's Haircut (camera: Rob Roll)" [2] "Gay Parade" [3] "Breast Cancer (complete)"
  - Boat Trip, undated; ID: 341.0009 (Box 42, Media ID: 341.0009)
    Original format: 16mm, 200 ft
  - Breast Cancer, undated; ID: 341.0018 (Box 42, Media ID: 341.0018)
  - Classroom, undated; ID: 341.0017 (Box 42, Media ID: 341.0017)
  - Duke Ellington and his Black Symphony, undated; ID: 341.0010 (Box 42, Media ID: 341.0010)
    Original Format: 16mm, 400 ft
  - Gay Dog, undated; ID: 341.0002 (Box 42, Media ID: 341.0002)
    Original Container Annotation: [1] "Gay Dog" [2] "Danielle - Double Suicide" [3] "Paradise in Drag"
  - "Gay Parade", 1977; ID: 341.0003 (Box 42, Media ID: 341.0003)
    Original format: 8mm
  - Going Swimming, undated; ID: 341.0025 (Box 42, Media ID: 341.0025)
  - I Change, undated; ID: 341.0015 (Box 42, Media ID: 341.0015)
    Original format: 16mm, 400 ft
  - Long Beach Regatta, undated; ID: 341.0011 (Box 42, Media ID: 341.0011)
  - Mexican Textiles & Designs, undated; ID: 341.0012 (Box 42, Media ID: 341.0012)
  - Mexico, undated; ID: 341.0008 (Box 42, Media ID: 341.0008)
  - "Mostlyt Ioutakes", undated; ID: 341.0006 (Box 42, Media ID: 341.0006)
    Original Container Annotation: [1] "Mostlyt ioutakes" [2] [Sexalphant] [3] "Iolo/Assassination of A.B." [4] "Breast Cancer/ Misc. San Fran." [5] "Grove Street Apt." [6] [Hari Krishna]
  - "Narcissus Lingerie + Taboo", undated; ID: 341.0004 (Box 42, Media ID: 341.0004, Box Digitized Access Files, File 341.0004)
    Currently available.
    8mm, 400 ft, Black and White, Silent, 5 minutes 40 seconds
  - Nude Corn Rov, undated; ID: 341.0005 (Box 42, Media ID: 341.0005)
    Original Container Annotation: [1] "Nude Corn Rov" [2] "Michael" [3] "Gery Kindy" [4] "Not Guilty - 10Lo"
  - Musical Performance, undated; ID: 341.0021 (Box 42, Media ID: 341.0021)
  - Musical Performance 2, undated; ID: 341.0026 (Box 42, Media ID: 341.0026)
  - Musical Performance 3 / Man in Woods, undated; ID: 341.0022 (Box 42, Media ID: 341.0022)
  - Shooting, undated; ID: 341.0023 (Box 42, Media ID: 341.0023)
  - "Thanks to Iolo etc.", undated; ID: 341.0007 (Box 42, Media ID: 341.0007)
    Original Container Annotation: [1] "Thanks to Iolo etc." [2] "[Hare] Krishna" [3] "Me by Eddington"
  - Threesome, undated; ID: 341.0014 (Box 42, Media ID: 341.0014)
  - Variety, undated; ID: 341.0016 (Box 42, Media ID: 341.0016)
  - Varios and Vida, undated; ID: 341.0013 (Box 42, Media ID: 341.0013)
- OVERSIZE Series I: Photographic Materials
  - Subseries C: Coursework
    - Assorted Contact Sheets, undated (Box 37)
    - "Contact Sheet 18" Poster Pamphlet, 1981 (Box Shared Fales 078, Folder 5)
    - "Dancing in the Streets" Poster, 1984 (Folder 10)